Learning-SICP学习小组
倾情制作
翻译&&时间轴：邓雄飞
压制&&特效：邓雄飞（Dysprosium）
校对：邓雄飞（Dysprosium）
特别感谢：裘宗燕教授
计算机程序的构造和解释
寄存机器
Register Machines
教授：我认为 到目前为止
PROFESSOR: Well, up 'til now, I suppose,
我们已经学习了很多关于
we've been learning about a lot of techniques for
组织程序以及操纵符号的技术
organizing big programs, symbolic manipulation a bit,
以及用来构建语言的技术
some of the technology that you use for establishing languages,
用一门语言去创建另一门语言
one in terms of another,
这在组织大型程序时非常有用
which is used for organizing very large programs.
实际上 我所知的最好的程序
In fact, the nicest programs I know
看起来更像是一堆语言
look more like a pile of languages
而不是将问题分解成若干部分
than like a decomposition of a problem into parts.
我想 此时此刻
Well, I suppose at this point,
关于这类东西的工作方式
there are still, however, a few mysteries
仍然存在一些谜团
about how this sort of stuff works.
因此 我现在需要
And so what we'd like to do now is
偏离原先的计划
diverge from the plan of
不再继续讲解如何组织大型程序
telling you how to organize big programs,
而是告诉你一些关于
and rather tell you something about the mechanisms
使这些事情可以起作用的机制
by which these things can be made to work.
这样做的主要是为了
The main reason for this is
揭秘
demystification, if you will,
剩下的很多谜团
that we have a lot of mysteries left,
比如说 如何控制程序的运行
like exactly how it is the case that a program is controlled,
计算机如何知晓下一步的动作
how a computer knows what the next thing to do is,
等等等等
or something like that.
我现在就要让你们清楚地知道
And what I'd like to do now is make that clear to you
就算你之前没有使用过计算机
that even if you've never played with a physical computer before,
但这种机制非常简单
the mechanism is really very simple,
你可以毫无问题地理解它
and that you can understand it completely with no trouble.
好吧 我们先来想象一个 --
So I'd like to start by imagining that we--
先说明一下 我们采用的方法是
well, the way we're going to do this, by the way,
把一些非常简单的Lisp程序
is we're going to take some very simple Lisp programs,
真的非常简单
very simple Lisp programs,
把它们转换成硬件
and transform them into hardware.
我不会考虑一些中间步骤
I'm not going to worry about some intermediate step
比如转换成某种现有的机器语言
of going through some existing computer machine language
然后来解释计算机是如何工作的
and then showing you how that computer works,
因为那不太明显
because that's not as illuminating.
所以我真正要向你展示的是
So what I'm really going to show you
如何构建一台机器来完成
is how a piece of machinery can be built
一项由你写的程序所描述的工作
to do a job that you have written down as a program.
而程序呢 实际上就是一个机器的描述
That program is, in fact, a description of a machine.
我们从一个非常简单的程序开始
We're going to start with a very simple program,
然后演示一些简单的机制
proceed to show you some simple mechanisms,
进而用更复杂的程序
proceed to a few more complicated programs,
然后又演示一个不那么复杂的程序
and then later show you a not very complicated program,
来演示求值器是如何变成硬件的
how the evaluator transforms into a piece of hardware.
当然 到那个时候
And of course at that point,
你就有了通用的转换算法
you have made the universal transition
并且可以用一个定义明确的硬件
and can execute any program imaginable
来执行任何可以想象的程序
with a piece of well-defined hardware.
那么 现在让我们开始
Well, let's start up now,
给你们关于这些东西的具体感觉
give you a real concrete feeling for this sort of thing.
我们先从一个非常简单的程序开始
Let's start with a very simple program.
这是欧几里得算法
Here's Euclid's algorithm.
它实际上比欧几里德算法更现代一些
It's actually a little bit more modern than Euclid's algorithm.
我想 用来计算两数最大公约数的欧几里得算法
Euclid's algorithm for computing the greatest common divisor of two numbers
是在公元前350年发明的
was invented 350 BC, I think.
它是已知最古老的算法
It's the oldest known algorithm.
我们先定义(GCD A B)
But here we're going to talk about GCD of A and B,
也就是用来计算A、B两数的最大公约数
the Greatest Common Divisor or two numbers, A and B.
这个算法相当简单
And the algorithm is extremely simple.
如果B等于0
If B is 0,
那么结果就是A
then the result is going to be A.
否则结果就是 (GCD B
Otherwise, the result is the GCD of B
(REMAINDER A B))
and the remainder when A is divided by B.
这里 我们定义了一个简单的迭代过程
So this we have here is a very simple iterative process.
这是一个简单的递归过程
This a simple recursive procedure,
也可以说这个过程是递归地定义的
recursively defined procedure, recursive definition,
但它产生的计算过程是迭代的
which yields an iterative process.
它的原理是 在每一步
And the way it works is that every step,
判断B是否为0
it determines whether B was zero.
如果B为0 那么A的值就是我们的答案
And if B is 0, we got the answer in A.
否则就进入下一个步骤
Otherwise, we make another step
其中A就变成旧的B
where A is the old B,
而B的值 是A旧值除B旧值的余数
and B is the remainder of the old A divided by the old B.
非常简单
Very simple.
现在 我已经通过这种方式
Now this, I've already told you
告诉了你一些机制
some of the mechanism by just saying it that way.
我是按时序告诉你们的
I said it in time.
我说 其中有特定的步骤
I said there are certain steps,
并且实际上
and that, in fact,
你可以在这里知道
one of the things you can see here
为什么这个过程是迭代的
is that one of the reasons why this is iterative
是因为最后一步无需额外信息来得到答案
is nothing is needed of the last step to get the answer.
所有运行此算法所需的信息都在A和B中
All of the information that's needed to run this algorithm is in A and B.
它有两个定义明确的状态变量
It has two well-defined state variables.
现在 我就要给你们定义一台机器
So I'm going to define a machine for you
用来计算GCD
can compute you GCDs.
我们来看看
Now let's see.
每台制造的计算机都是单进程计算机
Every computer that's ever been made that's a single-process computer,
而不是某种多处理器
as opposed to a multiprocessor of some sort,
都是按照相同的方案制定的
is made according to the same plan.
这种方案就是：计算机由两部分组成
The plan is the computer has two parts,
一部分叫数据通路
a part called the datapaths,
而另一部分叫控制器
and a part called the controller.
数据通路相当于你可能有的计算器
The datapaths correspond to a calculator that you might have.
它有一些寄存器 能够存储数据
It contains certain registers that remember things,
你们都用过计算器
and you've all used calculators.
它上面有一些按钮和指示灯
It has some buttons on it and some lights.
通过按下不同的按钮
And so by pushing the various buttons,
你可以使操作在寄存器内发生
you can cause operations to happen inside there among the registers,
并显示计算结果
and some of the results to be displayed.
它是完全机械式的
That's completely mechanical.
你可以认为那个盒子没有任何智能
You could imagine that box has no intelligence in it.
它能计算一个数的正弦也许令人吃惊
Now it might be very impressive that it can produce the sine of a number,
但它显然是机械式的
but that at least is apparently possibly mechanical.
至少 我可以像打开GCD机器一样打开它
At least, I could open that up in the same way I'm about to open GCD.
也就是说 它其中可能有一整台计算机
So this may have a whole computer inside of it,
但这并不有趣
but that's not interesting.
加法相当简单
Addition is certainly simple.
不借助额外机制就可以完成
That can be done without any further mechanism.
现在 如果我们来看另外的一部分：控制器
Now also, if we were to look at the other half, the controller,
这一部分也非常简单
that's a part that's dumb, too.
它负责按下按钮
It pushes the buttons.
它根据指令序列来按按钮
It pushes them according to the sequence,
指令是写在纸上的
which is written down on a piece of paper,
控制器还会观察指示灯
and observes the lights.
而且每隔一段 它就会来到指令序列中的一处
And every so often, it comes to a place in a sequence that says,
如果指示灯A亮 则执行某段指令
if light A is on, do this sequence.
否则执行另外的指令
Otherwise, do that sequence.
因此 这其中也没有什么复杂的
And thereby, there's no complexity there either.
那么 让我们来画一下
Well, let's just draw that
然后来感受一下它
and see what we feel about that.
为了计算GCD
So for computing GCDs,
你们要知道：这其中有一些寄存器
what I want you to think about is that there are these registers.
这里 寄存器就是一个存储数值的地方
A register is a place where I store a number, in this case.
这个寄存器存储的是A
And this one's called a.
而另外的这个存储的是B
And then there's another one for storing b.
现在我们来看看 有了这些寄存器后能做什么
Now we have to see what things we can do with these registers,
至于你能利用它做什么 并不是很明显
and they're not entirely obvious what you can do with them.
那么 我们必须看看需要用它们做什么
Well, we have to see what things we need to do with them.
我们来看看尝试求解的问题
We're looking at the problem we're trying to solve.
计算机设计的一个要点就是
One of the important things for designing a computer,
我想大多数设计师都不会照做
which I think most designers don't do,
也就是专注于待解的问题
is you stay the problem you want to solve
然后使用你研究问题所学到的东西
and then use what you learn from studying the problem you want to solve
把那些求解问题所需要的机制
to put in the mechanisms needed to solve it
融入正在构建的计算机中
in the computer you're building,
不多也不少
no more no less.
现在 可能你所要解决的问题
Now it may be that the problem you're trying to solve
是大家共有的问题
is everybody's problem,
这种情况下你需要构建
in which case you have to build in a universal
某种语言的通用解释器
interpreter of some language.
但是你添加的机制不能比
But you shouldn't put any more in than required
想构建的语言解释器的需求多
to build the universal interpreter of some language.
这一点 我们稍后来讨论
We'll worry about that in a second.
好了 让我们回到这里
OK, going back to here, let's see.
我们必须能够做什么？
What do we have to be able to do?
首先 我们能把B的值赋给A
Well, somehow, we have to be able to get B into A.
我们要能够把B的旧值赋给A
We have to be able to get the old value of B into the value of A.
因此 我们需要某种能够让数据流通的“路径”
So we have to have some path by which stuff can flow
而不管数据具体是什么
whatever this information is,
从B到A的通路
OK? from b to a.
我箭头来指示
I'm going to draw that with by an arrow
我们能够把B的值赋给A
saying that it is possible to move the contents of b into a,
从而替换A的旧值
replacing the value of a.
当你按下这里的按钮后
And there's a little button here which you push
就能够实现这个效果
which allows that to happen.
这个按钮就在这里
That's what the little x is here.
同样的
Now it's also the case
我还需要能够计算A除B的余数
that I have to be able to compute the remainder of a and b.
这可能混乱而又复杂
Now that may be a complicated mess.
但另一方面 我会把它放到一个小盒子中
On the other hand, I'm going to make it a small box.
如果有必要的话 我们可以打开那个盒子
If we have to, we may open up that box
看看其中有些什么
and look inside and see what it is.
这就是那个小盒子
So here, I'm going to have a little box,
我这么来画它
which I'm going to draw this way,
我把它叫做REM
which we'll call the remainder.
它接受A
And it's going to take in a.
同时也要接受B
That's going to take in b.
它有一个输出
And it's going to put out something,
也就是A除以B的余数
the remainder of a divided by b.
在这里 我们同样需要能够
Another thing we have to see here is
判断B是否等于0
that we have to be able to test whether b is equal to 0.
也就是说 总得有个东西
Well, that means somebody's got to be looking at--
去查询B的值
a thing that's looking at the value of b.
这是一个指示灯
I have a light bulb here
当B等于0时 它就会点亮
which lights up if b equals 0.
它就是干这个的
That's its job.
最后 因为我们希望
And finally, I suppose, because of the fact
A的新值是B的旧值
that we want the new value of a to be the old value of b,
同时B的新值是有关于A的
and simultaneously the new value of b to be something I've done with a,
如果我打算让机器
and if I plan to make my machine
一次只发生一件事
such that everything happens one at a time,
一次执行一个动作
one motion at a time,
并且我不能在一个寄存器中放两个数字
and I can't put two numbers in a register,
那么进行互换时 必须有另外的地方放置一个数字
then I have to have another place to put one while I'm interchanging.
对吧？
OK?
我不能同时交换两手的东西
I can't interchange the two things in my hands,
除非我一手拿两个
unless I either put two in one hand
然后从中取另外一个
and then pull it back the other way,
或者我先放下一个
or unless I put one down,
取得另一个后再像这样捡起来
pick it up, and put the other one, like that
除非我是耍杂技的
unless I'm a juggler,
当然正如大家所见 我并不是
which I'm not, as you can see,
这种情况下 我就会遇到时序错误
in which case I have a possibility of timing errors.
事实上 人们所做的许多类型的计算机设计
In fact, much of the type of computer design
都遇到了时序错误
people do involves timing errors,
或者潜在的时序错误
of some potential timing errors,
我不太喜欢这种错误
which I don't much like.
因此 出于这个原因
But. So for that reason,
我需要有一个地方来放置
I have to have a place to put the third thing down
其中的一个元素
the second one of them down.
因此 这里有一个寄存器
So I have a place called t,
用来存放临时值T
which is a register just for temporary, t,
上面有一个按钮
with a button on it.
我会使用它的结果
And then I'll take the result of that,
因为我需要把这个结果送入B
since I have to take that and put into b, over here,
我们会把结果像这样给送过来
we'll take the result of that and go like this,
这里同样有一个按钮
and a button here.
这就是GCD机器的数据通路
So that's the datapaths of a GCD machine.
那么 控制器又是怎样的呢？
Now what's the controller?
控制器同样很简单
Controller's a very simple thing, too.
机器具有状态
The machine has a state.
我喜欢形象地把它们比作迷宫
The way I like to visualize that is that I've got a maze.
这个迷宫的各处是通过直接的箭头连接的
And the maze has a bunch of places connected by directed arrows.
而我有一颗弹珠
And what I have is a marble,
它代表了控制器的状态
which represents the state of the controller.
弹珠在迷宫中四处滚动
The marble rolls around in the maze.
当然 这种类比因能量的原因而不成立
Of course, this analogy breaks down for energy reasons.
有时我不得不将弹珠泵到顶部
I sometimes have to pump the marble up to the top,
不然它就会成为一台永动机
because it's going to otherwise be a perpetual motion machine.
但不用担心那么多
But not worrying about that,
这并不是一个物理比喻
this is not a physical analogy.
弹珠到处滚动
This marble rolls around.
就像弹球机一样
And every time it rolls around certain bumpers,
每次当它滚动到一些缓冲器时
like in a pinball machine,
它就会按下这些按钮
it pushes one of these buttons.
它也会经常来到一个分支区域
And every so often, it comes to a place, which is a division,
它要在这里做选择
where it has to make a choice.
然后有一个由这个组件控制的挡板
And there's a flap, which is controlled by this.
所以这是一个非常机械化的思考方式
So that's a really mechanical way of thinking about it.
当然 真实计算机中的控制器
Of course, controllers not these days, are not built that way
并不是这样的
in real computers.
而是由一些ROM和状态寄存器构成
They're built with a little bit of ROM and a state register.
但曾几何时 像DEC、PDP-6这些个机器
But there was a time, like the DEC PDP-6,
它们的控制器就是我们说的那样
where that's how you built the controller of a machine.
延迟线上有一些比特信息
There was a bit that ran around the delay line,
它随着时间的推移而触发事件
and it triggered things as it went by.
然后回到开始并再次轮回
And it would come back to the beginning and get fed round again.
当然 还有各种各样的错误
And of course, there were all sorts of great bugs you could have
比如两个比特的信息 -- 对应两个弹珠
like two bits going around, two marbles.
机器也会丢失弹珠
And then the machine has lost its marbles.
这也会发生
That happens, too.
好吧
Oh, well.
无论如何 对于这台机器
So anyway, for this machine,
我想要这么来做
what I have to do is the following.
迷宫从这里开始
I'm going to start my maze here.
我首先要做的是
And the first thing I've got to do,
用一个你们非常熟悉的流程图记号
is in a notation which many of you are familiar with,
这是一个判断：B是否为0
is b equal to zero, a test.
如果判断为是的话
And there's a possibility, either yes,
那我就做完了
in which case I'm done.
否则的话
Otherwise, if no,
我就不得不滚动一些缓冲器
then I'm going have to roll over some bumpers.
按照下列顺序执行
I'm going to do it in the following order.
我想向这样来做一个互换游戏
I want to, I want to do this interchange game.
首先 因为我需要A和B
Now first, since I need both a and b,
但首先 -- 虽然并不是必要的
but then the first-- and this is not necessary--
我需要先把它们收集起来
I want to collect this.
这里的值要送入到B中
This is the thing that's going to go into b.
因此 我会说
So I'm going to say,
用A和B的值来计算这个
take this, which depends upon both a and b,
并把算得的余数放到这里
and put the remainder into here.
因此 我首先要按下这个按钮
So I'm going to push this button first.
然后我要把B的值送入A
Then, I'm going to transfer b to a,
通过按这个钮来实现
push that button,
然后我再把临时值送入B
and then I transfer the temporary into b,
通过这个按钮实现
push that button.
这是一个相当时序化的机器
So a very sequential machine,
它非常的低效
it's very inefficient.
但目前来说还好
But that's fine right now.
我们来为按钮命名
We're going to name the buttons,
T←R
t gets remainder.
A←B
a gets b.
B←T
And b gets t.
然后我要来到这里
And then I'm going to go around here
也就是回到开始的地方
and it's to go back to start.
在这里 我们看到了什么？
And if you look, what are we seeing here?
我们看到各种各样的 --
We're seeing the various--
我们真正拥有的是某种机械连接
what I really have is some sort of mechanical connection,
其中T←R控制了这个东西
where t gets r controls this thing.
A←B控制了这个东西
And I have here that a gets b controls this fellow over here,
而这里的这个东西
and this fellow over here.
同学们 这简直太恶劣了
Boy, that's absolutely pessimal,
一点也没有优化
the inverse of optimal.
我画的所有线条都相互交叉
Every line heads across every other line the way I drew it.
我想B←T控制的是这个
I suppose this goes here, b gets t.
现在 我就要运行这台机器了
Now I'd like to run this machine.
但是在我运行它之前
But before I run the machine,
我想写下它的控制器的描述
I want to write down a description of this controller,
以便使你们相信
just so you can see that these things,
这些东西可以组织成某种良好的语言
of course, as usual, can be written down in some nice language,
这样我们就不必总是像这样画图
so that we don't have to always draw these diagrams.
图示的缺陷之一 就是占用了太多空间
One of the problems with diagrams is that they take up a lot of space.
对于这样的一个小型机器来说
And for a machine this small,
它占用了两块黑板
it takes two blackboards.
而一台求值器机器
For a machine that's the evaluator machine,
我就很难将它画在这间屋子里了
I have trouble putting it into this room,
尽管它还不是非常大
even though it isn't very big.
因此我要为它构造一门小型语言
So I'm going to make a little language for this
用来描述这个机器
that's just a description of that,
(DEFIME-MACHINE GCD
saying define a machine we'll call GCD.
当然 一旦我们有了像这样的描述
Of course, once we have something like this,
我们就能够模拟该机器
we have a simulator for it.
我之所以想构建这种形式的语言
And the reason why we want to build a language in this form,
是因为我们能够立即操纵这些表达式
is because all of a sudden we can manipulate these expressions that I'm writing down.
因此 我也就能够
And then of course I can write things I can
代数地操作 或者模拟这些东西
algebraically manipulate these things, simulate them
以及各种各样我想进行的操作
all that sort of things that I might want to do,
或者还可以把它们转换成布局图 谁知道呢？
perhaps transform them as a layout, who knows.
一旦我有了寄存器的良好表示
Once I have a nice representation of registers,
它有一些寄存器
it has certain registers,
记作(REGISTERS A B T)
which we can call A, B, and T.
它还有控制器
And there's a controller.
实际上 更好的做法是让它更显式一些
Actually, a better language, which would be more explicit,
也就是说 为每一个按钮命名
would be one which named every button
并指明它们的操作
also and said what it did.
比如说这个按钮
Like, this button
会让T的值送入到B中
causes the contents of T to go to the contents of B.
但我却不想这么做
Well I don't want to do that,
因为这样会让代码难以阅读
because it's actually harder to read to do that,
也会占用更多空间
and it takes up more space.
所以我会把相关的指令写在控制器中
So I'm going to have that in the instructions written in the controller.
这样就隐式地指明了具体的操作
It's going to be implicit what the operations are.
可以通过阅读代码推断出来
They can be deduced by reading these
并收集所有可以完成的不同事情
and collecting together all the different things that can be done.
我们来看一看
We look and see, see...
我们来看下这些东西是什么吧
Well, let's just look at what these things are.
首先是一个循环
There's a little loop that we go around
先是一条分支指令
which says branch,
这个就对应了机器中的小挡板
this is the representation of the little flap
它决定了你在此处的走向
that decides which way you go here,
判断 -- 取B的值 并判断是否为0
if 0, OK, fetch of B, the contents of B,
如果B的值是0
and if the contents of B is 0,
那么就跳转到一个叫DONE的地方
then go to a place called done.
现在 你们在这里看到的是
Now, one thing you're seeing here,
这个看起来非常像传统计算机语言
this looks very much like a traditional computer language.
但你们所见的是
And what you're seeing here
一些个标签
is things like labels
它们代表着存放了一系列指令的地方
that represent places in a sequence written down as a sequence.
之所以需要它们
The reason why they're needed
是因为在这里
is because over here,
我表达了“循环”的概念
I've written something with loops.
但是如果我是在写英文之类的文本
But if I'm writing English text, or something like that,
就很难去引用一个位置
it's hard to refer to a place.
我没有箭头
I don't have arrows.
箭头是通过
Arrows are represented by giving names
给箭头所指的地方命名来表示的
to the places where the arrows terminate,
并通过名字来引用
and then referring to them by those names.
这只是一种编码
Now this is just an encoding.
而不是某种魔法
There's nothing magical about things like that.
接下来我们要做的是
Next thing we're going to do is we're going to say,
我们如何来实现T←R
how do we do T gets R?
非常简单 用ASSIGN
Oh, that's easy enough, assign.
我们把余数赋值给T
We assign to T the remainder.
ASSIGN就是按钮的名字
Assign is the name of the button.
就是按按钮的家伙
That's the button-pusher.
把余数赋给T
Assign to T the remainder,
这个操作是这样表示的
and here's the representation of the operation,
取A、B的值 相除得到余数
when we divide the fetch of A by the fetch of B.
同时 我们也要取B的值 赋给A
And we're also going to assign to A the fetch of B,
再取T的值赋给B
assign to B the result of getting the contents of T.
现在 我需要引用这个开头
And now I have to refer to the beginning here.
呃 我为什么不把这里叫做LOOP呢？
I see, why don't I call that loop like I have here?
这就是如何引用这个箭头
OK? So that's that reference to that arrow.
当执行到DONE时 就完成了所有操作
And when we're done, we're done.
我们来到了这里 所有指令的结尾
We go to here, which is the end of the thing.
这段文字化描述的就是
So here's just a written representation
我们在这里画的一小部分机器
of this fragment of machinery that we've drawn here.
下面 我就要运行它
Now the next thing I'd like to do is run this.
我想让你们感受一下它的运行
I want us to feel it running.
从来没有做过这个 你必须做一次
Never done this before, you got to do it once.
让我们以一个具体的问题来演示
So let's take a particular problem.
假设我们想要计算
Suppose we want to compute the GCD
30和42的最大公约数
of a equals 30 and b equals 42.
我现在不知道结果是多少
I have no idea what that is right now.
但我知道A=30而B=42
But a 30 and b is 42.
我就这么着开始
So that's how I start this thing up.
那么 我首先要做些什么呢？
Well, what's the first thing I do?
我先判断B是否为0：否
I say is B equal to 0, no.
然后计算A除B的余数 并赋给T
Then assign to T the remainder of the fetch of A and the fetch of B.
当然 30除以42的余数就是30自己
Well the remainder of 30 when divided by 42 is itself 30.
按下那个按钮
Push that button.
现在弹珠就滚动到了这里
Now the marble has rolled to here.
A←B
A gets B.
又按下了这个按钮
That pushes this button.
因此42来到了这里
So 42 moves into here.
B←T
B gets T.
按下了这个按钮
Push that button.
30来到了这里
The 30 goes here.
这样我就交换了它们
Let met just interchange them.
我们再来看看 回到开始
Now let's see, go back to the beginning.
B为0么？不
B 0, no.
将余数赋给T
T gets the remainder.
我想 42除以30的余数是12
I suppose the remainder when dividing 42 by 30 is 12.
按下这个钮
I push that one.
下面 我想让30来到这里
Next thing I do is allow the 30 to go to here,
按下这个钮 让12来到这里
push this one, allow the 12 to go to here.
然后继续
OK? Go around this thing.
程序执行完了么？
Is that done?
并没有
No.
现在 我需要求解30除以12的余数
How about-- so now I have to find out the remainder of 30 divided by 12.
我想答案是6
And I believe that's 6.
按下这个钮 6就到了这里
So 6 goes here on this button push.
然后我又按下这个钮
Then the next thing I push is this one,
这就让12来到了这里
which the 12 goes into here.
然后我又按下这个按钮
Then I push this button.
6就来到了这里
The 6 gets into here.
6等于0么？
Is 6 equal to 0?
不等于
No.
好的
OK.
因此这时
So then at that point,
接下来又要计算余数
the next thing to do is divide it.
哦 这个的余数是0
Ooh, this has got a remainder of 0.
看起来我们就快完成了
Looks like we're almost done.
将6从这里挪到这里
Move the 6 over here next.
0移动到这里
0 over here.
0等于0么？
Is the answer 0?
是的
Yes.
B的值等于0 因此答案就是A的值
B is 0, therefore the answer is in A.
因此答案就是6
The answer is 6.
这确实是正确的答案
And indeed that's right,
因为如果我们回过头审视最初的问题
because if we look at the original problem,
我们知道30=2×3×5
what we have is 30 is 2 times 3 times 5,
42=2×3×7
and 42 is 2 times 3 times 7.
因此最大公约数就是2×3
So the greatest common divisor is 2 times 3,
也就是6
which is 6.
我们通常在这里画另外一条线
Now normally, we write one other little line here,
为了使它更清晰一点
just to make it a little bit clearer,
在这两者之间建立了联系
which is that we leave in a connection saying
小挡板需要根据这个指示灯来工作
that this light is the guy that that flap looks at.
当然 跟我给你们展示的东西相比
Of course, any real machine has a lot more
真实计算机的组件更加复杂
complicated things in it than what I've just shown you.
让我们来看看第一张幻灯片
Let's look for a second at the first still store.
哇
Wow.
我们看到 我们想要做的就是
Well you see, for example, one thing we might want to do
IO形式的操作
is worry about the operations that are of IO form.
我们需要从外部搜集一些东西
And we may have to collect something from the outside.
因此 对我们的状态机器来说
So a state machine that we might have,
它们的控制器
the controller may have to,
可能会从某处取得某值
may have to, for example, get a value from something
将它们放入寄存器并从中读取
and put register a to load it up.
我还可以把另外的值加载到寄存器B中
I have to master load up register b with another value.
稍后 当执行完毕后
And then later, when I'm done,
我想要输出结果
I might want to print the answer out.
当然 答案或简单或复杂
And of course, that might be either simple or complicated.
我写代码的时候 总假设PRINT很简单
I'm writing, assuming print is very simple,
READ也很简单
and read is very simple.
但实际上 在真实世界中
But in fact, in the real world,
这些都是非常复杂的操作
those are very complicated operations,
跟你尝试求解的问题相比
fairly, usually much, much larger and more complicated
它们通常更加庞大而复杂
than the thing you're doing as your problem you're trying to solve.
另一方面 我犹记得
On the other hand, I can remember a time when,
使用IBM 7090一类的计算机的时候
I remember using IBM 7090 computer of sorts,
它的READ和WRITE只能操作单个对象
where things like read and write of a single object,
也就是一个数字
a single number, a number,
这就是一个基本的IO操作
is a primitive operation of the IO controller.
我们这里有同样的操作
OK? And so we have that kind of thing in there.
在这样的一台机器中
And in such a machine,
我们实际上在做什么？
well, what are we really doing?
我们看到 这个叫做“READ”的组件是数据源头
We're just saying that there's a source over here called "read"
这个操作总是返回一个值
which is an operation which always has a value.
我们可以把它看做 总是返回一个值
We have to think about this as always having a value
它可以赋给寄存器A或B
which can be gated into either register a or b.
而PRINT这个过程呢
And print is some sort of thing
当你正确连接它的时候
which when you gate it appropriately,
当你按下上面的按钮
when you push the button on it,
就会打印出当前寄存器A中的值
will cause a print of the value that's currently in register a.
这非常普通
Nothing very exciting.
这是我们想要的一种功能
So that's one sort of thing you might want to have.
但这里还有些其它事情需要我们担忧
But these are also other things that are a little bit worrisome.
比如说 这里我使用了一些复杂的机制
Like I've used here some complicated mechanisms.
我们这里有REMAINDER组件
What you see here is remainder.
这是个什么东西呢？
What is that?
求取余数的计算过程并不是那么“显然”
That may not be so obvious how to compute.
如果我们把这个组件给拆开
It may be something which when you open it up,
就会得到一整台机器
you get a whole machine.
事实就是这样的
OK? In fact, that's true.
举例来说 如果要编程实现REMAINDER
For example, if I write down the program for remainder,
最简单的算法就是 不断地做减法
the simplest program for it is by repeated subtraction.
这是因为 除法可以通过
Because of course, division can be done
对整数不断做减法来实现
by repeated subtraction of numbers, of integers.
N除以D的余数不外乎就是
So the remainder of N divided by D
如果N小于D的话
is nothing more than if N is less than D,
答案就是N
then the result is N.
否则的话就是
Otherwise, it's the remainder
N先减去D
when we subtract D from N with respect to D,
再除以D的余数
when divided by D.
天啊 这个看起来就像是GCD程序
Gee, this looks just like the GCD program.
当然 这个不是求余数的最优算法
Of course, it's not a very nice way to do remainders.
在实际中 你应该使用那些
You'd really want to use something like
二进制运算、移位运算等操作
binary notation and shift and things like that in a practical computer.
但关键点就是
But the point of that is
如果我把这些组件打开
that if I open this thing up,
我可能会发现其中有一台计算机
I might find inside of it a computer.
现在我们就知道它的原理了
Oh, we know how to do that.
因为我们就造过一台
We just made one.
这些个机器都大同小异
And it could be another thing just like this.
另外一方面
On the other hand,
我们可能想要构建一台更高效
we might want to make a more efficient
组织更精良的机器
or better-structured machine,
比如说 多次利用其中的寄存器
or maybe make use of some of the registers more than once,
或者是硬件设计者能想到的其它可怕混乱
or some horrible mess like that that hardware designers like to do,
等等原因
and for very good reasons.
比如说 你们所见的这台机器
So for example, here's a machine that you see,
不是让你们去细读它的结构的
which you're not supposed to be able to read.
它有些复杂 对吧？
It's a little bit complicated. OK?
但它实际上是
But what it is is the integration of
整合了REMAINDER的GCD机器
remainder into the GCD machine.
并且实际上 它没有多余的寄存器
And it takes, in fact, no more registers.
数据通路上有三个寄存器
There are three registers in the datapaths. OK?
但现在 这里有个减法器
But now there's a subtractor.
又有两个东西被测试
There are two things that are tested.
B等于0么？
Is b equal to 0,
T小于B么？
or is t less than b?
而至于这一块的控制器
And then the controller, which you see over here,
并不会更加复杂
is not much more complicated.
它有两个循环
But it has two loops in it,
最主要的循环是计算GCD的
one of which is the main one for doing the GCD,
而另一条是减法循环
and one of which is the subtraction loop
是用来计算余数的子操作
for doing the remainder sub-operation.
当然 还有一种思考方式
And there are ways, of course, of,
就是把求余数程序
if you think about it, taking the remainder program.
如果我把那边的REMAINDER机器
If I take remainder, as you see over there
当作LAMBDA表达式
as a lambda expression,
代换到GCD程序的REMAINDER中
substitute it in for remainder over here in the GCD program,
然后再做一些化简
OK, then do some simplification
代换其中的A和B
by substituting a and b for remainder in there,
那么 我就可以展开这个循环
then I can unwind this loop.
那么我就可以通过
And I can get this piece of machinery
LAMBDA表达式的基本代数化简
by basically, a little bit of simplification
来得到这台机器
algebraic simplification on the lambda expressions.
我想 你们已经见识了一个非常简单的机器了
So I suppose you've seen your first very simple machines now.
有什么疑问么？
Are there any questions?
很好
Good.
看起来很容易 难道不是吗？
This looks easy, doesn't it?
好吧 休息一下 谢谢大家
Thank you. I suppose, take a break.
[音乐]
[JESU, JOY OF MAN'S DESIRING]
《计算机程序的构造和解释》
讲师：哈罗德·艾伯森教授 及 格兰德·杰·萨斯曼教授
寄存机器
教授：好吧
PROFESSOR: Well, let's see.
现在 你们已经知道如何去把迭代过程
Now you know how to make an iterative procedure,
或者是产生迭代计算的过程
or a procedure that yields an iterative process,
变成一台机器
turn into a machine.
我想 接下来我们就应该考虑
I suppose the next thing we want to do is worry about things
如何来处理递归过程了
that reveal recursive processes.
我们先从一个简单的阶乘过程开始
So let's play with a simple factorial procedure.
(DEFINE (FACT N)
We define factorial of N to be
如果N=1 那么结果就是1
if n is 1, the result is 1,
为了减少模拟它的工作量 我就使用1
using 1 right now to decrease the amount of work I have to do to simulate it,
否则结果就是(* N (FACT (- N 1)))
else it's times N factorial N minus 1.
正如你们所知 这个程序的不同之处在于
And what's different with this program, as you know,
这里 我在计算(FACT (- N 1))之后
is that after I've computed factorial of N minus 1 here,
我要对结果做一些运算
I have to do something to the result.
我要将它与N相乘
I have to multiply it by N.
将这台机器可视化的唯一途径就是
So the only way I can visualize what this machine is doing,
首先 由于--
because of the fact--
请你们这么来想
think of it this way,
这里 我有一台机器
that I have a machine out here
而这台机器又需要某个阶乘机器来计算结果
which somehow needs a factorial machine in order to compute its answer.
但外面的这台机器
But this machine, the outer machine,
又需要在调用内部阶乘机器
has to exist before and after
的前后都要存在
the factorial machine, which is inside.
然而在迭代情况中
Whereas in the iterative case,
外面的机器不需要
the outer machine doesn't need to exist
在内部机器运行后保持存在
after the inner machine is running,
这是因为你不需要回到
because you never need to go back
外部机器来进行其它操作
to the outer machine to do anything.
因此 我们这里的问题是
So here we have a problem
我们的机器内部
where we have a machine
有一个同样的机器
which has the same machine inside of it,
一台无穷大的机器
an infinitely large machine.
这里面也有其它的东西 比如乘法器
And it's got other things inside of it, like a multiplier,
它接收输入
which takes some inputs,
这是-1操作
and there's a minus 1 box,
等等
and things like that.
你们可以想象 -- 它就是这个样子的
You know, You can imagine that's what it looks like.
但重要之处就在于
But the important thing is that here I have
内部机器执行之前与执行之后
something that happens before and after,
外部机器中都进行了一些运算
in the outer machine, the execution of the inner machine.
因此这台机器必须有“生命”
So this machine has to have a life.
外部机器需要在内部机器的两个时间点保持存在
It has to exist on both times sides of this machine.
因此 我就需要有一个地方来保存
So somehow, I have to have a place to store
维持外部机器运转的数据
the things that this thing needs to run.
现实世界中不存在无穷的对象
Infinite objects don't exist in the real world.
我们要做的就是营造一种假象
What we have to do is arrange an illusion
一种无穷对象的假象
that we have an infinite object,
我们在某处有无穷的硬件资源
we have an infinite amount of hardware somewhere.
现在 这个假象非常重要
Now of course, illusion's all that really matters.
如果我们能保证
If we can arrange
每次当你查看某个无穷对象时
that every time you look at some infinite object,
你所要观察的那部分存在
the part of it that you look at is there,
那么就不需要实际上的“无穷”
then it's as infinite as you need it to be.
当然 这里面我们想做的就是
And of course, one of the things we might want to do,
来看下这里的东西
just look at this thing over here,
这是我们目前为止的结构
is the organization that we've had so far
这些结构呢
organization that we've had so far
是机器的几大部分
involves having a part of the machine,
比如控制器
which is the controller,
它在这里
which sits right over here,
它相当简单 并且是有穷的
which is perfectly finite and very simple.
我们还有数据通路
We have some datapaths,
它由寄存器和运算器组成
which consist of registers and operators.
现在我提议
And what I propose to do here is decompose
把机器分成两部分
the machine into two parts,
这样 其中一部分全部是有穷的
such that there is a part which is fundamentally finite,
而另一部分 可以保存无穷数据中的一部分
and some part where a certain amount of infinite stuff can be kept.
换句话说 这部分也非常简单
On the other hand this is very simple
但并非无穷 只是非常大而已
and really isn't infinite, but it's just very large.
但它非常简单
But it's so simple
以至于能够廉价地大量生产
that it could be cheaply reproduced in such large amounts,
它就是内存
we call it memory,
我们可以利用它来构造栈结构
OK? that we can make a structure called a stack out of it
事实上 这就使得我们
which will allow us to, in fact,
能够模拟无穷机器的存在
simulate the existence of an infinite machine
也就是那些递归嵌套的机器
which is made out of a recursive nest of many machines.
而它的原理则是
And the way it's going to work is that
我们要在栈上存放必要的信息
we're going to store in this place called the stack
用于内部机器执行完毕后
the information required after the inner machine runs
继续外部机器的操作
to resume the operation of the outer machine.
因此它会记住
So it will remember
关于外部机器生命期的重要数据
the important things about the life of the outer machine
这些是进行计算所必需的
that will be needed for this computation.
当然
Since, of course,
由于这些机器是通过递归的方式嵌套的
these machines are nested in a recursive manner,
因此 栈的存取方式也会是
then in fact the stack will only be accessed in a manner
也会是后进先出的
which is the last thing that goes in is the first thing that comes out.
因此我们只需要存取
So we'll only need to access
这个栈内存的一小部分
some little part of this stack memory.
好吧 让我们来试一试
OK, well, let's do it.
我已经给你们画好了数据通路
I'm going to build you a datapath now,
现在该布置控制器了
and I'm going to write the controller.
然后我们来运行一下 观察实际工作原理
And then we're going to execute this to see how you do it.
还好阶乘机器不是特别的复杂
So the factorial machine isn't so bad.
它有一个VAL寄存器
It's going to have a register called the value,
这是用来存储答案的
where the answer is going to be stored,
还有一个寄存器N
and a registered called N,
它里面存储的是要计算阶乘的数
which is where the number I'm taking factorial will be stored, factorial of.
为了满足某些情况
And it will be necessary in some instances
我们要连接VAL和N
to connect VAL to N.
事实上 如果我在这里返回N
In fact, one nice case of this is if I just said over here,
也是正确的 因为这时N就等于1
N, because that would be right for N equal 1N.
这样的话 我就可以把结果移动过去
And I could just move the answer over there if that's important.
但我现在不考虑这个问题
I'm not worried about that right now.
我还需要做一些事情
And there are things I have to be able to do.
就像我们在这里看到的 我们还需要
Like I have to be able to, as we see here,
用VAL的值乘以N
multiply N by something in VAL,
因为VAL是计算阶乘的结果
because VAL is the result of computing factorial.
我需要把算得的结果送回VAL
And I have to put the result back into VAL.
所以这里我们看到
So here we can see
N的阶乘就是
that the result of computing a factorial
N乘以某个阶乘
is N times the result of computing a factorial.
而VAL就代表了内部阶乘的结果
VAL will be the representation of the answer of the inner factorial.
因此 在这里我需要有一个乘法器
And so I'm going to have to have a multiplier here,
它的参数有：N以及VAL
which is going to sample the value of N and the value of VAL
并且 像这样把计算结果送回VAL
OK? and put the result back into VAL like that.
我也需要知道N是否为1
I'm also going to have to be able to see if N is 1.
因此我需要一个指示灯
So I need a light bulb.
另外 我想我还需要
And I suppose the other thing I'm going to need to have
一个组件来减小N
is a way of decrementing N.
所以这里有一个递减器
So I'm going to have a decrementer,
它接收参数N 将结果送回N
which takes N and is going to put back the result into N.
这基本上就是我的机器所需要的东西了
That's pretty much what I need in my machine.
然而 我还需要一些个东西
Now, there's a little bit else I need.
一个稍微复杂一点的东西
It's a little bit more complicated,
因为我需要有一种方式能够存储
because I'm also going to need a way to store,
必要的一些信息
to save away, the things that are going to be needed
以便计算完子阶乘后
for resuming the computation of a factorial
恢复原始阶乘的计算
after I've done a sub-factorial.
需要哪些信息呢?
What's that?
首先就是N
One thing I need is N.
因此 我要在这里构造一个栈
So I'm going to build here a thing called a stack.
所谓的栈就是
The stack is
一大堆连续的空间
a bunch of stuff that I'm going to write in sequentially.
我不知道它到底有多深
I don't know how long it is.
栈越深 无穷的假象营造得就越好
The longer it is, the better my illusion of infinity.
我还需要有一种方法 能够把
And I'm going to have to have a way of getting stuff
N中的值放入栈中
out of N and into the stack
反过来也是
and vice versa.
因此我需要一条像这样的连接
So I'm going to need a connection like this,
它是双向的
which is two-way,
通过它 我就可以在某个时间
whereby I can save the value of N
把N的值存储起来
and then restore it some other time through that connection.
这就是栈
This is the stack.
我还需要一种方法来记住
I also need a way of remembering
我现在计算到外部程序的哪个地方了
where I was in the computation of factorial in the outer program.
现在 对于这台机器来说
Now in the case of this machine,
这并不是什么问题
it isn't very much a problem.
FACT总是返回在
Factorial always returns,
一个跟N相乘的地方
has to go back to the place where we multiply by N,
除了最后的一次
except for the last time,
它返回到需要FACT最终答案的地方
when it has to return to whatever needs the factorial
或者是'DONE、'STOP之类的
or go to done or stop.
然而 通常来说
However, in general,
我需要记住我去过哪些地方
I'm going to have to remember where I have been,
因为 我可能从其它地方调用FACT
because I might have computed factorial from somewhere else.
我需要返回到那个地方 并从那里继续
I have to go back to that place and continue there.
因此 我需要有一种方法能够
So I'm going to have to have some way of taking the place
记住有穷状态控制器中弹珠的位置
where the marble is in the finite state controller,
也就是控制器的状态
the state of the controller,
并将它存储在栈中
and storing that in the stack as well.
我也需要有一种方法
And I'm going to have to have ways of restoring that
能够恢复弹珠的状态
back to the state of the-- the marble.
因此 我需要有一种将弹珠归位的能力
So I have to have something that moves the marble to the right place.
现在 我们有一个地方用于存储弹珠
Well, we're going to have a place which is the marble now.
它被称作“继续”寄存器
And it's called the continue register,
记作CONTINUE
called continue,
下一次调用(GOTO CONTINUE)时
which is the place to put the marble
弹珠就会去向这个地方
next time I go to continue.
它就是用来干这个的
That's what that's for.
因此 它和控制器之间应该有一条通路
And so there's got to be some path from that into the controller.
我也能够将它存储在栈上
I also have to have some way of saving that on the stack.
我也能够把它设置成各种常量
And I have to have some way of setting that up to have various constants,
某一些常量
a certain fixed number of constants.
这非常容易实现
And that's very easy to arrange.
我们现在这里设一些常量
So let's have some constants here.
我们把这个记作AFTER-FACT
We'll call this one after-fact.
这个常量
And that's a constant
会送入CONTINUE寄存器
which will get into the continue register,
另外一个寄存器是FACT-DONE
and also another one called fact-done.
这就是我想要构建的机器
So this is the machine I want to build.
至少是数据通路部分
That's its datapaths, at least.
这里还混合了一些控制器
And it mixes a little with the controller here,
这是因为我需要记住我当前的位置
because of the fact that I have to remember where I was
并将我恢复到该位置
and restore myself to that place.
现在 让我们来编写控制器对应的程序
But let's write the program now which represents the controller.
我就把DEFINE-MACHINE和寄存器列表给省略了
I'm not going to write the define machine thing and the register list,
因为它们无关紧要
because that's not very interesting.
我就直接写那些跟控制器有关的
I'm just going to write down the sequence of instructions
指令序列
that constitute the controller.
首先是(ASSIGN CONTINUE DONE)
So we have assign, to set up, continue to done.
然后是一个循环
We have a loop
先判断 如果1=N 那么就跳转
which says branch if equal 1 fetch N,
那么就进入归纳的基本步骤
if N is 1, then go to the base step of the induction,
也就是最简单的情况
the simple case.
否则的话
Otherwise,
我就要记住那些
I have to remember the things that are necessary
计算子阶乘所必须的信息
to perform a sub-factorial.
我需要来带这里 以便计算子阶乘
I'm going to go over here, and I have to perform a sub-factorial.
所以我需要记住 完成它需要些什么
So I have to remember what's needed to do that
需要记住我计算完之后需要哪些东西
remember what's needed after I will be done with that.
看到了吗 我要做些糟糕的事儿
See, I'm about to do something terrible.
我要去修改N的值
I'm about to change the value of N.
但是它又需要记住N的旧值
But this guy has to know the old value of N.
但是为了计算子阶乘
But in order to make the sub-factorial work,
我又需要修改N的值
I have to change the value of N.
因此 我就得记住N的旧值
So I have to remember the old value.
我也需要记住我的位置
And I also have to remember where I've been.
因此 我保存CONTINUE的值
So I save up continue.
这条指令 就是用来将数据入栈的
And this is an instruction that says, put something in the stack.
将CONTINUE寄存器的值保存起来
Save the contents of the continuation register,
在本例中也就是DONE
which in this case is done,
因为稍后我也会修改它
because later I'm going to change that, too,
因为我也需要回到AFTER-FACT
because I need to go back to after-fact, as well.
我们来看看
We'll see that.
我们需要存储N 因为稍后会用到
We save N, because I'm going to need that for later.
(ASSIGN N (-1+ (FETCH N)))
Assign to N the decrement of fetch N.
(ASSIGN CONTINUE ...
Assign continue,
我看一下 --
we're going to look at this now,
AFT)
to after, we'll call it.
这个名字很好
That's a good name for this,
因为它短小精炼 很适合用在这里
a little bit easier and shorter, and fits in here.
现在 来看看我怎么做
Now look what I'm doing here.
我说 如果ANSWER是1的话
I'm saying, if the answer is 1,
那程序就结束了
OK, I'm done.
我只需要取得这个答案
I'm going to have to just get the answer.
否则我就要保存当前的继续以及N的值
Otherwise, I'm going to save the continuation, save N,
然后让N减1
make N one less than N,
注意 我先要跳转到某处
remember I'm going to come back to someplace else,
然后来到这里 计算另外的阶乘
and go back and start doing another factorial.
然而 这之中又有了另外的机器
OK? However, I've got a different machine in me now.
其中N=1 CONTINUE是其它值
N is 1, and continue is something else.
N=N-1
N is N minus 1.
再我完成这个之后
Now after I'm done with that,
我会来到这里
I can go there.
我会恢复N的旧值
I will restore the old value of N,
也就是这里SAVE的逆运算
which is the opposite of this save over here.
然后恢复CONTINUE
I will restore the continuation.
然后我又会来到这里
I will then go to here.
(ASSIGN VAL
I will assign to the VAL register
(* (FETCH N) (FETCH VAL)))
the product of N and fetch VAL.
（闭合括号中）
VAL fetch product assign.
这样操作就完成了
And then I will be done.
子阶乘的结果就存储在了VAL中
I will have my answer to the sub-factorial in VAL.
这个时候
At that point,
我就要返回到
I'm going to return
CONTINUE所指向的地方
by going to the place where the continuation is pointing.
也就是(GOTO (FETCH CONTINUE))
That says, go to fetch continue.
最后就是基本情况的那步
And then I have finally a base step,
也就是一个立即值
which is the immediate answer.
(ASSIGN VAL (FETCH N))
Assign to VAL fetch N,
(GOTO (FETCH CONTINUE))
and go to fetch continue.
这样我就完成了
And then I'm done.
现在 我们用一个非常简单的例子来运行一下
Now let's see how this executes on a very simple case,
因为这样我们就将看到
because then we'll see
栈是如何帮助我们完成计算的
the use of this stack to do the job we need.
这是计算的静态描述
This is statically what it's doing,
我们需要动态地观察它
but we have look dynamically at this.
因此 让我们来看看
So let's see.
首先我们要把CONTINUE设置为DONE
First thing we do is continue gets done.
这是我通过按下这个钮来实现的
The way that happened is I pushed this.
我们还是把它记作DONE吧
Let's call that done the way I have it.
我按下这个按钮
I push that button.
DONE就进到了这里
Done goes into there.
现在 我还要为这些东西设置初始值
Now I also have to set this thing up to have an initial value.
让我们考虑3的阶乘
Let's consider a factorial of three,
这个例子非常简单
a simple case.
我们的栈从这里开始增长
And we're going to start out with our stack growing over here.
栈有它们自己的内部状态
Stacks have their own little internal state
用来标识栈顶位置
saying where they are,
也就是下一个可写位置
where the next place I'm going to write is.
现在我们问 N=1么？
So now we say, is N 1?
当然不等于
The answer is no.
因此现在我要保存CONTINUE
So now I'm going to save continue, bang.
现在 DONE就来到了这里
Now that done goes in here.
然后 这个指针移动到了这里
And this moves to here,
下次我要把数据写到这里
the next place I'm going to write.
保存N的值--也就是3
Save N 3.
对吧？
OK?
N←N-1
Assign to N the decrement of N.
也就是说 我得按下这个钮
That means I've pushed this button.
这就变成了2
This becomes 2.
COUNTINUE←AFT
OK? Assign to continue aft.
因此我要按下这个钮
So I've pushed that button.
AFT就进入了这里
Aft goes in here.
然后 跳转到LOOP 我们就来到了这里
OK, now go to loop, bang, so up to here.
N=1么？当然不
Is N 1? No
因此我又要保存CONTINUE
So I have to save continue.
CONTINUE的值是什么呢？
What's continue?
目前是AFT
Continue is aft.
按下这个按钮
Push this button.
这个指针移动到了这里
So this moves to here.
我还要保存N
I have to save N.
N在那里 它的值是2
N is over here. I got to 2.
按下这个按钮
Push that button.
2就进入了这里
So a 2 gets written there.
然后这个指针移动到了这里
And then this thing moves down here.
保存N之后 又赋N←N-1
OK, save N. Assign N to the decrement of N.
它就变成了1
This becomes a 1.
CONTINUE←AFT
Assign continue to aft.
AFT又进入了这里
A-F-T gets written there again.
然后又跳转到LOOP
Go to loop.
N等于1么？
Is N equal to 1?
是的 那么答案就是1
Oh, yes, the answer is 1.
跳转到BASE那一步
OK, go to base step.
(ASSIGN VAL (FETCH N))
Assign to VAL fetch of N.
按下这个 1就进入到了这里
Bang, 1 gets put in there. OK?
(GOTO (FETCH CONTINUE))
Go to fetch continue.
来看下CONTINUE寄存器
So we look in continue.
基本上来说 我按下这里的按钮 进入到控制器
Basically, I'm pushing a button over here that goes to the controller.
CONTINUE寄存器就变成了AFT
The continue becomes aft,
这样一下子 程序就运行到了这里
and all of a sudden, the program's running here.
现在 我就需要恢复外部的阶乘了
I now have to restore the outer version of factorial.
因此我们来到这里
So we go here.
我们先要恢复N
We say, restore N.
这就意味着 我们要使用这里的内容
So restore N means take the contents that's here.
按下这个按钮 2就会来到这里
Push this button, and it goes into here, 2,
然后指针会向上移动
and the pointer moves up.
恢复CONTINUE寄存器也非常简单
Restore continue, pretty easy.
来按下这个按钮
Go push this button.
然后 AFT又一次进入到这里
And then aft gets written in here again.
同时 这个指针也要上移
That means this thing moves up.
这样就避开了栈上的其它东西
I've gotten rid of something else on my stack.
然后我来到这里
Right, then I go to here,
也就是(ASSIGN VAL (* N VAL))
which says, assign to VAL the product of N and VAL.
然后我按下这个按钮
So I push this button over here, bang.
2乘以1等于2
2 times 1 gives me a 2,
我写到这里
get written there.
然后是(GOTO (FETCH CONTINUE))
OK? Go to fetch continue.
CONTINUE现在是AFT 我跳转到AFT
Continue is aft. I go to aft.
AFT首先要恢复N
OK? Aft says restore N.
恢复N指的是
Do your restore N,
我把这里的值 也就是3
means I take the value over here, which is 3,
按下这里的按钮
push this up to here,
然后把它放到这里 N
and move it into here, N.
然后 我们按下这个钮
Now it's pushing that button.
接下来我就要恢复CONTINUE
The next thing I do is restore continue.
CONTINUE寄存器现在成为了DONE
Continue is now going to become done.
当我按下这个钮后 指针就移动到了这里
So this moves up here when I push this button.
DONE可能从此之后不在这里了
Done may or may be there anymore,
对此我并不感兴趣 但它现在一定在这里
I'm not interested, but it certainly is here.
下一步 我将要把VAL赋值为
Next thing I do is assign to VAL
N乘以VAL的值
the product of the fetch of N and the fetch of VAL.
按下这里的按钮就可以实现
That's pushing this button over here, bang.
2乘以3等于6
2 times 3 is 6.
所以这里我就得到了6
So I get a 6 over here.
下一步是(GOTO (FETCH CONTINUE))
OK? And go to fetch continue,
哦 跳转到DONE 这样我就完成了
whoops, I go to done, and I'm done.
最后的答案是6
And my answer is 6,
你们可以在VAL寄存器中看到
as you can see in the VAL register.
事实上
And in fact,
栈又回到了它初始的状态
the stack is in the state it originally was in.
在使用像栈这样的东西中 有一些原则
Now there's a bit of discipline in using these things like stacks
我们需要注意
that we have to be careful of.
我们会在下一小节中介绍
And we'll see that in the next segment.
但首先 对于这一小节所讲的内容
But first I want to ask if there are any questions for this.
有什么问题么？
Are there any questions?
Ron 请讲
Yes, Ron.
学生：当你越过了栈的顶端会怎样--
AUDIENCE: What happens when you roll off the end of the stack with--
教授：你所谓的“越过”是指什么？
PROFESSOR: What do you mean, roll off of?
学生：如果我们的N是一个很大的数
AUDIENCE: Well, the largest number-- a larger starting point of N
就需要更多的内存 对吧？
requires more memory, correct?
教授：是的
PROFESSOR: Oh, yes.
这样 我就需要一个足够大的栈
Well, I need to have a long enough stack.
你想问 如果破坏了无穷存储的假象会发生什么？
You say, what if I violate my illusion?
学生：是的
AUDIENCE: Yes.
教授：那么 这些魔法就不再起效了
PROFESSOR: Well, then the magic doesn't work. OK?
真相就是 任何机器都是有穷的
The truth of the matter is that every machine is finite.
而对于像这样的过程
And for a procedure like this,
我只能进行有限数量的子阶乘计算
there's a limit to the number of sub-factorials I could have.
想一想 我们之前讲解的Y组合子
Remember when we were doing the y-operator a while ago,
我们指出 存在一系列的指数过程
we pointed out that there was a sequence of exponentiation procedures,
其中每一个都要比前一个更精准
each of which was a little better than the previous one.
现在 我们看到了如何实现这个数学理念
Well, we're now seeing how we implement that mathematical idea.
这个取极限的过程
The limiting process
只有当你取到极限时才足够精准
is only so good as as far as you take the limit.
如果你仔细想想 我这里用了什么
If you think about it, what am I using here?
对于这个过程的每一次递归
I'm using about two chunks, pieces of memory
我用了大概两块内存
for iteration for every recursion of this process.
如果我们尝试计算10000的阶乘
If we try to compute factorial of 10,000,
这并不会花掉很多内存
that's not a lot of memory.
虽然这是一个很大的数
On the other hand, it's an awful big number.
因此 实际的问题就是值不值得
So the question is, is that a valuable thing in this case.
但这并不是这种实现的局限
But it really turns out not to be a terrible limit,
因为内存非常低廉
because memory is el cheapo,
但人力资源却相当昂贵
and people are pretty expensive.
好吧 我们先休息一下 谢谢大家
OK, thank you, let's take a break.
[音乐]
[JESU, JOY OF MAN'S DESIRING]
《计算机程序的构造和解释》
讲师：哈罗德·艾伯森教授 及 格兰德·杰·萨斯曼教授
寄存机器
教授：我们讲解了
PROFESSOR: Well, let's see.
如果进行简单的迭代计算
What I've shown you now is how to do a simple iterative process
以及简单的递归计算
and a simple recursive process.
我只想通过向你们展示一些针对特定应用的
I just want to summarize the design of simple machines
更加复杂的设计
for specific applications
来总结简单机器的设计
by showing you a little bit more complicated design,
也就是同时递归地调用两个斐波那契函数
that of a thing that does doubly recursive Fibonacci,
因为它会向我们表明 并且我们会理解
because it will indicate to us, and we'll understand,
一些关于栈正常工作
a bit about the conventions required
所需要遵守的约定
for making stacks operate correctly.
现在 让我们来看看
So let's see.
先让我在黑板上写下
I'm just going to write down, first of all,
将要翻译的程序
the program I'm going to translate.
这是一个斐波那契过程
I need a Fibonacci procedure,
它非常的简单
it's very simple, which says, if
如果N小于2 那么结果就是N
N is less than 2, the result is N,
否则就是(FIB (- N 1))加上
otherwise it's the sum of Fib of N minus 1
(FIB (- N 2))
and Fib of N minus 2.
这就是我的计划
That's the plan I have here.
现在 我们要来写下这台机器的控制器
And we're just going to write down the controller for such a machine.
首先 我们假设有一个寄存器N
We're going to assume that there are registers, N,
里面存放的是斐波那契函数的自变量
which holds the number we're taking Fibonacci of,
而计算结果会存放在VAL寄存器中
VAL, which is where the answer is going to get put,
CONTINUE寄存器会和控制器相连
and continue, which is the thing that's linked to the controller,
就跟之前一样
like before.
但我不会再去画数据通路了
But I'm not going to draw another physical datapath,
因为它和之前的那个差不多
because it's pretty much the same as the last one you've seen.
当然 关于计算的最神奇的事情之一
And of course, one of the most amazing things about computation
就是一段时间后
is that after a while,
你构建了一个又一个的小功能
you build up a little more features and a few more features,
你就一下子拥有了需要的一切
and all of the sudden, you've got everything you need.
这种效率是非常了不起的
So it's remarkable that it just gets there so fast.
构造制作一台通用计算机不需要太多的东西
I don't need much more to make a universal computer.
总之 我们来看看斐波那契机器的控制器
But in any case, let's look at the controller for the Fibonacci thing.
我首先要做的是
First thing I want to do is
通过为CONTINUE寄存器赋值
start the thing up by assign to continue
赋FIB-DONE来启动计算
a place called done, called Fib-done here.
这就意味着在这里
So that means that somewhere over here,
我需要有一个标签 FIB-DONE
I'm going to have a label, Fib-done,
当我来到这个地方后
which is the place where I go
机器就停止了
when I want the machine to stop.
这就是这个标签的作用
That's what that is.
然后我要创建一个循环
And I'm going to make up a loop.
我要来到这里来启动FIB的计算
It's a place I'm going to go to in order to start up computing a Fib.
无论这时 N等于多少
Whatever is in N at this point,
斐波那契函数都会被计算
Fibonacci will be computed of,
然后会返回到由CONTINUE寄存器指向的地方
and we will return to the place specified by continue.
因此你们将在这里看到
So what you're going to see here at this place,
我想要在做一个约定
what I want here is the contract
我用注释的形式来说明这个约定
that says, I'm going to write this with a comment syntax,
也就是N中存储的是参数
the contract is N contains arg, the argument.
而CONTINUE存储的是接收者
Continue is the recipient.
这个约定就是这样的
And that's where it is.
因此每当我来到这里
At this point, if I ever go to this place,
我希望这个约定是成立的
I'm expecting this to be true,
这些计算斐波那契函数所需要的参数
the argument for computing the Fibonacci.
接下来我想做的是分支
Now the next thing I want to do is to branch.
如果N小于2
And if N is less than 2--
随便说一下 我使用的语法看起来像Lisp
by the way, I'm using what looks like Lisp syntax.
但它并不是Lisp
This is not Lisp.
它们运行不起来
This does not run.
我在这里写的并不是一个简单的Lisp程序
What I'm writing here does not run as a simple Lisp program.
这是另一门语言的表示形式
This is a representation of another language.
我之所以使用这种满是括号的语法
The reason I'm using the syntax of parentheses and so on
是因为我刚好使用Lisp系统
is because I tend to use a Lisp system
来为这门语言编写解释器
to write an interpreter for this
这就使得我们能够模拟
which allows me to simulate
我想要构建的机器
the machine I'm trying to build.
我不想让你们感到困惑 认为这是Lisp代码
I don't want to confuse this to think that this is Lisp code.
只是我用了很多Lisp组件
It's just I'm using a lot of the pieces of Lisp.
我在Lisp中嵌入了一门语言
I'm embedding a language in Lisp,
把Lisp当作组件
using Lisp as pieces
这样就能让我的模拟工作变得简单
to make my process of making my simulator easy.
我从Lisp中继承了这些属性
So I'm inheriting from Lisp all of its properties.
(FETCH N) 2)
Fetch of N 2,
成立的话 我想要跳转到IMMEDIATE-ANSWER这个地方
I want to go to a place called immediate answer.
这是基本步骤
It's the base step.
它对应在这里
Now, that's somewhere over here,
也就是在FIB-DONE的上方
just above done.
我们稍后就会看到
And we'll see it later.
现在 对于一般情况来说
Now, in the general case,
也就是我现在要写的
which is the part I'm going to write down now,
是这样的
let's just do it.
首先呢 我需要调用斐波那契函数两次
Well, first of all, I'm going to have to call Fibonacci twice.
在每一次中 -- 至少在其中一次
In each case-- well, in one case at least,
我得需要知道该怎么做
I'm going to have to know what to do
才能回过头来进行另外一个计算
to come back and do the next one.
我需要记住
I have to remember,
我计算完第一个FIB了么？
have I done the first Fib,
或者第二个也计算完了？
or have I done the second one?
我是该返回到计算第二个FIB的地方
Do I have to come back to the place where I do the second Fib,
还是回到执行ADD的地方
or do I have to come back to the place where I do the add?
无论哪种情况 我都需要--
In both cases I going to need, I don't
在第一个计算第一个FIB时
In the first case, over the first Fibonacci,
我需要保存N的值 来计算第二个FIB
I'm going to need the value of N for computing for the second one.
因此我要把这些东西保存起来
So I have to store some of these things up.
首先要保存CONTINUE
So first I'm going to save continue.
也就是答案的接收者
That's who needs the answer.
我之所以要这么做
And the reason I'm doing that
是因为我现在要把CONTINUE赋值为
is because I'm about to assign continue
我待会儿想要返回的地方
to the place which is the place I want to go to after.
我们把它叫做AFTER-FIB-N-1
Let's call it Fib-N-minus-1,
这个长名字 非常具有Lisp的命名特点
big long name, classic Lisp name.
这是因为我先要计算第一个(FIB (- N 1))
Because I'm going to compute the first Fib of N minus 1,
计算完成之后
and then after that,
我想要回过头来做些其它事
I want to come back and do something else.
而AFTER-FIB-N-1这个地方
That's the place I want to go to after I've done
就是我计算完第一个FIB后应该返回的地方
the first Fibonacci calculation.
接下来我要保存N
And I want to do a save of N,
因为我稍后需要用到它
because I'm going to need it later, after that.
在这里 我就已经
Now I'm going to, at this point,
准备好计算(FIB (- N 1))了
get ready to do the Fibonacci of N minus 1.
(ASSIGN N (- (FETCH N) 1))
So assign to N the difference of the fetch of N and 1.
现在 该跳转到FIB-LOOP了
Now I'm ready to go back to doing the Fib loop.
我满足我立下的约定么？
Do I have... Have I satisfied my contract?
答案是是的
And the answer is yes.
N现在存储的是N-1 这是我需要的
N contains N minus 1, which is what I need.
而CONTINUE包含的是计算完成后 返回的目的地
OK? Continue contains a place I want to go to when I'm done
也就是计算(FIB (- N 1))完成之后
with calculating FIB N minus 1.
因此我满足了这些约定
So I've satisfied the contract.
因此 我就可以在这里写下一个标签
And therefore, I can write down here a tag, after, a label,
AFTER-FIB-N-1
after-Fib-N-minus-1.
在这里 我又该做些什么呢？
Now what am I going to do here?
在这里
Here's a place
我已经准备好去计算(FIB (- N 2))了
where I now have to get ready to do Fib of N minus 2.
但是为了计算(FIB (- N 2))
But in order to do a Fib of N minus 2,
首先 我不知道
look, I don't know.
这里 我已经改变了N
I've clobbered my N over here.
或者在这个时候 我的N总是不断地
And presumably my N is counted down
向1或者0递减
all the way to 1 or 0 or something at this point.
所以我不知道N寄存器中存储的到底是什么
So I don't know what the value of N in the N register is.
我想要保存在栈中的N的值
I want the value of N that was on the stack
也就是我在这里保存的值
that I saved over here
这样我就可以在这里恢复它
so that could restore it over here.
我在这里存储的N
I saved up the value of N,
是这个时间点N的值
which is this value of N at this point,
因此计算完(FIB (- N 1))之后我可以恢复它
so that I could restore it after computing Fib of N minus 1,
这样的话 我就可以计算(- N 2)
so that I could count that down to N minus 2
然后就可以计算(FIB (- N 2))的值
and then compute Fib of N minus 2.
现在让我们来恢复它
So let's restore that.
(RESTORE N)
Restore of N.
现在我要做一件很教条的事
Now I'm about to do something which is superstitious,
我们会尽快将其删除
and we will remove it shortly.
如果你们愿意的话
I am about to finish the sequence
我将要结束子过程调用
of doing the subroutine call, if you will.
接下来我会说
I'm going to say, well,
因为我保存了CONTINUE
I also saved up the continuation,
现在就要去恢复它
since I'm going to restore it now.
但实际上 我并不需要这么做
But actually, I don't have to,
因为我并不需要用到它
because I'm not going to need it.
我们稍后会修正它
We'll fix that in a second.
现在我们来恢复CONTINUE
So we'll do a restore of continue,
通常来说 我都会这么做
which is what I would in general need to do.
我们将要看到
And we're just going to see whats called
编译器领域中的“窥孔优化”
what you would call in the compiler world a peephole optimization,
来帮我们消除这个不必要的步骤
which says, whoops, you didn't have to do that.
因此 我即将要做的就是
OK, so the next thing I see here
准备好计算(FIB (- N 2))
is that I have to get ready now to do Fibonacci of N minus 2.
但是我不再需要保存N了
But I don't have to save N anymore.
原因就是
The reason why I don't have to save N anymore
计算完(FIB (- N 2))之后 我就不需要N了
is because I don't need N after I've done Fib of N minus 2,
因为 我接下来要做的就是ADD
because the next thing I do is add.
因此 我会这么来设置N
So I'm just going to set up my N that way.
(ASSIGN N (- (FETCH N) 2))
Assign N minus difference of fetch N and 2.
现在我需要结束
Now I have to finish the setup
调用(FIB (- N 2))的设置过程了
for calling Fibonacci of N minus 2.
我需要保存CONTINUE
Well, I have to save up continue
然后把CONTINUE赋值为
and assign continue, continue,
AFTER-FIB-N-2
to the place which is after Fib N 2,
对应了那边代码的某处
that place over here somewhere.
然而 我需要非常小心
However, I've got to be very careful.
而(FIB (- N 1))的值
The old value, the value of Fib of N minus 1,
我稍后会用到
I'm going to need later.
(FIB (- N 1))的值
The value of Fibonacci of N minus 1,
我需要它的值
I'm going to need.
我不能去改变它
And I can't clobber it,
因为我需要用它来加上(FIB (- N 2))
because I'm going to have to add it to the value of Fib of N minus 2.
它是存放在寄存器中的 因此我需要保存它
That's in the value register, so I'm going to save it.
所以现在我要用(SAVE VAL)来保存它
So I have to save this right now, save up VAL.
现在我就可以调用子过程了
And now I can go off to my subroutine,
(GOTO FIB-LOOP)
go to Fib loop.
现在 在进行更进一步计算之前
Now before I go any further
在结束这个程序之前
and finish this program,
我想审视一下目前的代码片段
I just want to look at this segment so far
这里有一系列的指令
and see, oh yes, there's a sequence of instructions here, if you will
我可以对它们进行某些操作
that I can do something about.
这里 我有一个操作用来恢复CONTINUE
Here I have a restore of continue,
一个操作用来保存CONTINUE
a save of continue,
然后给CONTINUE赋值
and then an assign of continue,
但这之中没有CONTINUE的其它引用
with no other references to continue in between.
恢复之后又保存
The restore followed by the save
使得栈没有被修改
leaves the stack unchanged.
唯一的区别就是 我给CONTINUE寄存器赋了值
The only difference is that I set the continue register to a value,
一个存放在栈上的值
which is the value that was on the stack.
由于我现在改变了这个值
Since I now clobber that value,
但这之间并没有引用这个值
as in it was never referenced,
这些指令就是不必要的
these instructions are unnecessary.
因此我们会移除它们
So we will remove these.
但我只有先把它们写出来 才会发现这个情况
But I couldn't have seen that unless I had written them down.
真是这样吗？
Was that really true?
我并不知道
Well, I don't know.
现在 我们要开始计算(FIB (- N 2))了
OK, so we've now gone off to compute Fibonacci of N minus 2.
计算完毕后
So after that,
我们又要做什么呢？
what are we going to do?
我想 我们首先要做的就是
Well, I suppose the first thing we have to do--
我们有两件事要做
we've got two things.
目前VAL寄存器中的值 是有意义的
We've got a thing in the value register which is now valuable.
然而 栈上也有一个数据
We also have a thing on the stack
需要恢复到VAL寄存器中
can be restored into the value register.
现在我需要非常小心的是
And what I have to be careful with now
正确地给它们排序 以便计算乘法
is I want to shuffle this right so I can do the multiply.
现在 我可能会使用不同的约定
Now there are various conventions I might use,
但我现在会采用非常挑剔的一种
but I'm going to be very picky and say,
栈上数据来自于哪个寄存器 就恢复到那个寄存器中
I'm only going to restore into a register I've saved from.
如果是这样的话 在这里我就要进行洗牌
If that's the case, I have to do a shuffle here.
这跟我有多少只手是同样的问题
It's the same problem with how many hands I have.
现在我要给N赋值
So I'm going to assign to N,
因为我现在不再需要N了 N是无用的
because I'm not going to need N anymore, N is useless,
获取当前VAL寄存器的值
the current value of VAL,
也就是(FIB (- N 2))的值
which was the value of Fib of N minus 2.
现在 我就要恢复VAL寄存器了
And I'm going to restore the value register now.
这个RESTORE匹配这里的SAVE
This restore matches this save.
如果你非常仔细地研究发生了什么
And if you're very careful and examine very carefully what goes on,
会发现 RESTORE和SAVE总是成对的
OK? restores and saves are always matched.
现在 这里有个额外的SAVE
Now there's an outstanding save,
当然 我们很快就会消灭它
of course, that we have to get rid of soon.
恢复完VAL寄存器后
And so I restored the value register.
我就要恢复CONTINUE寄存器了
Now I restore the continue one,
它匹配了这个
which matches this one,
从这里到这里
dot, dot, dot, dot, dot, dot, dot, down to here,
这样就恢复了继续
Now restoring that continuation.
这个表达式继续是由(FIB N)产生的
That continuation is a continuation of Fib of N,
也就是我正尝试求解的
which is the problem I was trying to solve,
最主要的问题
a major problem I'm trying to solve.
我需要把(FIB N)的答案返回给这个继续
So that's the guy I have to go back to who wants Fib of N.
在我意识到N并不小于2之前
I saved them all the way up here
我一直保存着它们
when I realized N was not less than 2.
因此 我需要进行一个复杂的运算
And so I had to do a complicated operation.
现在万事俱备
Now I've got everything I need to do it.
因此我要恢复它们
So I'm going to restore that,
(ASSIGN VAL (+ (FETCH VAL) (FETCH N)))
assign to VAL the sum of fetch VAL and fetch of N
然后跳转到CONTINUE
and go to continue.
然后我就从(FIB N)中返回了出来
So now I've returned from computing Fibonacci of N,
也就是FIB的一般情况
the general case.
现在还有一些细节 需要我们填充
Now what's left is we have to fix up a few details,
比如归纳的基本情况：可以立即得到答案
like there's the base case of this induction, immediate answer,
这不过就是
as, which is nothing more than
(ASSIGN VAL (FETCH N)
assign to VAL fetch of N,
因为N小于2
because N was less than 2,
因此答案就是N
and therefore, the answer is N
跟源程序是一致的
in our original program,
(GOTO (FETCH CONTINUE))
and return continue--
最后就结束了
bobble, bobble almost-- and finally Fib done.
这是个相当复杂的程序
So that's a fairly complicated program.
我之所以给你们演示这个程序
And the reason I wanted you see to that
是因为我想让你们见识
is because I want you to see the particular
我所遵守的栈使用准则
flavors of stack discipline that I was obeying.
第一点就是 我不想保存那些
It was first of all, I don't want to save anything
稍后不需要的值
that I'm not going to need later.
我非常地小心
I was being very careful.
这非常重要
And it's very important.
当然 人们还制定了其它的准则
And there are all sorts of other disciplines people make
来操作栈帧之类的东西
with frames and things like that of some sort,
这些准则中 那些不再需要的东西
where you save all sorts of junk
也需要保存并恢复
you're not going to need later and restore it
因为从某种意义上来说 这样做更容易些
because, in some sense, it's easier to do that.
但这会带来各种灾难
That's going to lead to various disasters,
我们稍后就会见识一些
which we'll see a little later.
只保存那些你稍后需要的值 这很关键
It's crucial to save exactly what you're going to need later.
这是非常重要的理念
It's an important idea.
无论谁保存了一个值 都应该由他来恢复
And the responsibility of that is whoever saves something
因为他需要这个值
is the guy who restores it, because he needs it.
在这样的准则中
And in such discipline,
你可以发现哪些数据是不必要的
you can see what things are unnecessary,
哪些操作又是不重要的
operations that are unimportant.
我还想告诉你们
Now, one other thing I want to tell you about is very simple
当然 你们看到的并不是全部的图景
is that, of course, the picture you see is not the whole picture.
假设我的系统中
Supposing I had systems
具有像CAR、CDR、CONS这样的运算
had things like other operations, CAR, CDR, CONS,
或者创建一个向量
building a vector
并引用它的第N个元素
and referencing the nth element of it,
等等运算
or things like that.
然而 就在这个层次的细节来说
Well, at this level of detail, whatever it is,
我们可以在数据通路中把它们视为基本运算
we can conceptualize those as primitive operations in the datapath.
换句话说 我们可以认为 有一台机器
In other words, we could say that some machine that, for example, has
包含了APPEND机器
has the append machine,
它通过(CONS (CAR X)
which has to do cons of the CAR of x
(APPEND (CDR X) Y)来实现
with the append of the CDR of x and y,
哦 天啊 这就跟阶乘机器有相同的结构
well, gee, that's exactly the same as the factorial structure.
当然 它有相同的结构
Well, it's got about the same structure.
我们有什么呢？
And what do we have?
我们有某种东西 其中有
We have some sort of things in it
诸如X、Y之类的寄存器
which may be registers, x and y,
有时X会移动到Y中
and then x has to somehow move to y sometimes,
或者X会取得Y的值
x has to get the value of y.
我们或许要需要能够进行CONS运算
And then we may have to be able to do something which is a cons.
我记不清这个系统中是否需要这样的东西
I don't remember if I need to like this is in this system,
但CONS有点类似于减法器或加法器之类的东西
but cons is sort of like subtract or add or something.
它把两个东西结合起来
It combines two things,
然后产生一个序对
producing a thing which is the cons,
然后会把输出结果送入到这里
which we may then think goes into there.
可能还有一个叫做CAR的组件
And then maybe a thing called the CAR,
它的结果是 -- 某个东西的CAR部分
which will produce-- I can get the CAR or something.
我还可以取得某物的CDR部分 等等
And maybe I can get the CDR of something, and so on.
但我们不应该害怕这么说
But we shouldn't be too afraid of saying things this way,
因为最坏的情况不过
because the worst that could happen
当我们打开CONS后
is if we open up cons,
会发现其中存在某台机器
what we're going to find is some machine.
CONS可能会与CAR和CDR有所重叠
And cons may in fact overlap with CAR and CDR, and it always does,
就像加法和减法有所重叠一样
in the same way that plus and minus overlap,
它们本质上都是一样的
and really the same business.
CONS、CAR和CDR将会有所重叠
CONS, CAR, and CDR are going to overlap,
我们会发现其中有小型控制器
and we're going to find a little controller,
小型的数据通路
a little datapath,
其中还有一些寄存器
which may have some registers in it,
一些其它的像这样的东西
some stuff like that.
并且 也许在这之中
And maybe inside it,
可能也有无穷的部分
there may also be an infinite part,
又或者是半无穷的 之类的
a part that's semi-infinite or something,
这些都是统一的东西
which is a lot of very uniform stuff,
也就是我们所谓的“内存”
which we'll call memory.
有限的内存也能无穷地存储 对此我一点也不吃惊
And I wouldn't be so horrified if that were the way it works.
实际上它就是这样的 我们之后就会了解
In fact, it does, and we'll talk about that later.
那么 有什么疑问么？
So are there any questions?
天啊！你们都一言不发
Gee, what an unquestioning audience.
假设我说得都是谎言吧！
Suppose I tell you a horrible pile of lies.
好吧
OK.
谢谢大家
Well, thank you.
我们下课吧！
Let's take our break.
MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
本项目主页
https://github.com/DeathKing/Learning-SICP